<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Divine light, manifesting the love of God unto the whole world: with the true church. Wherein the holy spirit of truth manifesteth the glory of God in Christ, exalting Christ, a spirituall Christ, and all-saving Jesus; shewing that Christ is a sure foundation, and chief corner-stone, for all spirituall building, unto the raising up lively hopes for all people to proceed in beleeving the great mercies, and loving kindnesses of our God in Christ, in whom God hath redeemed us his saints, and all; having wrought all things for us, and all in Christ, wherein wee are made perfect. Sent forth by the minister of the Lord Jesus, whom he hath appointed his servant for the good of all: in bringing glad tidings of good things unto the whole creation. Esai.52.7.13.The lord will worke for the manifestation of his truth, in this his due time.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81569</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873631</idno>
  <idno type="VID">159779</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248523638</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1722</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E343_14</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R993</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873631</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99873631e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81569)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 159779)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 56:E343[14])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Divine light, manifesting the love of God unto the whole world: with the true church. Wherein the holy spirit of truth manifesteth the glory of God in Christ, exalting Christ, a spirituall Christ, and all-saving Jesus; shewing that Christ is a sure foundation, and chief corner-stone, for all spirituall building, unto the raising up lively hopes for all people to proceed in beleeving the great mercies, and loving kindnesses of our God in Christ, in whom God hath redeemed us his saints, and all; having wrought all things for us, and all in Christ, wherein wee are made perfect. Sent forth by the minister of the Lord Jesus, whom he hath appointed his servant for the good of all: in bringing glad tidings of good things unto the whole creation. Esai.52.7.13.The lord will worke for the manifestation of his truth, in this his due time.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 25, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeer. 1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 7th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Jesus Christ --  Divinity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:159779:1"/>
            <p>DIVINE LIGHT, Manifesting THE LOVE OF GOD UNTO THE WHOLE WORLD: With the True CHVRCH.</p>
            <p>Wherein the holy Spirit of Truth manifesteth the Glory of <hi>GOD</hi> in <hi>CHRIST,</hi> Exalting CHRIST, a spirituall CHRIST, and All-saving JESUS; shewing that Christ is a sure Foundation, and Chief <hi>Corner-Stone,</hi> for all Spirituall building, unto the raising up live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hopes for all People to proceed in Beleeving the great Mercies, and loving kindnesses of our GOD in CHRIST, in whom God hath Redeemed us his Saints, and <hi>All;</hi> having wrought all things for us, and all in CHRIST, wherein wee are made perfect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sent forth by the Minister of the Lord JESƲS, whom He hath Appointed his Servant for the</hi> Good of All:</p>
            <q>
               <p>In bringing Glad Tidings of Good Things unto the whole Creation.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Esai.</hi> 52.7.13.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>And Hee said, it is a Light thing, that thou shouldest be my Servant, to raise up the Tribes of <hi>Jacob,</hi> And to restore the Preserved of <hi>Israel.</hi> I will give thee also for a Light to the Gentiles; That thou maist be my Salvation unto the ends of the Earth.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Esai. 49.6.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>The <hi>LORD</hi> will worke for the manifestation of his Truth, in this his due time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed in the Year.</hi> 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:159779:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:159779:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y these the Spirit maintaineth, and discovereth the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ, Apostate <hi>Arians, Egyptians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.26.</note>
               <hi>Sodomites and Drunkards</hi> of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> the Devills in-carnate, which are, or shall be found to denie the Covenant of <hi>Generall Redemption;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Isa.</hi> 1.10. <hi>chap.</hi> 28.1, 2, 3.</note> And so denie God and Christ, and their owne Salvation. These are the <hi>Antichristi</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">From these <hi>Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sti Apostate Arians,</hi> that denie the holy Covenant of <hi>Generall. Redemption,</hi> all other Heresies and Schisme proceed to the denying God, Christ, and their owne Salvation, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der faire pretenses, as their Father the Devill: Sophistry teacheth them too much in their acting of wickednesse, In their Hipocrisies, in denying God and his Truth, of perfecting all in CHRIST; wherein they Blaspheam his Name, as also deny their own Salvation. <hi>Esai.</hi> 52.5. <hi>&amp; Joh.</hi> 8.43, 44. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1, 2.</note>
               <hi>Apostate Arians</hi> in chief, who by the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Grand Devill <hi>Mallice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.2.</note> Sophisti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call <hi>Mallice,</hi> the very Devill, and old Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent that deceived <hi>Eve,</hi> and brought in Transgression, hath caused curse and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the afflicting in the Pit, wherein there is no water, the disobedient soules and spirits which have trespassed against God and CHRIST, and their owne Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, by the Abomination of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christi Apostate Arianisme.</hi> This <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichristi Apostate Arianisme,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>Dragon,</hi> that Old Serent, called
<pb facs="tcp:159779:3"/>the Devill and Satan, which deceiveth the whole world, by denying the Power of God in the perfecting his Creation in <hi>CHRIST,</hi> in that be denieth the holy <hi>Covenant</hi> of <hi>Generall Redemption:</hi> but this Dragon, and Grand Devill, <hi>ANTICHRISTI APO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STATE ARIANISME,</hi> must be cast out of heaven, <hi>(The Church,)</hi> and all his Angels, <hi>(The false Ministers, and Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Magistrates,)</hi> must be cast out with him. <hi>Then shall the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens Rejoyce, and the Earth shall Sing with Triumph, for the fall of</hi> BABILON.</p>
            <p>Jere. <hi>51.47, 28, 53.</hi> Rev. <hi>18.2, 3.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:159779:3"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Herefore by this our Epistle, we Defie the Great <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ,</hi> and all <hi>Antichristians,</hi> who denie the Covenant of <hi>Generall Redemption,</hi> and so denie their owne Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, but to the comfort of the Christian Spirit, who draweth neer to seek God aright; Wee Proclaime, the Riches and Grace of Our God, through JESUS CHRIST; yea to all, as hee is a Spirituall Christ, and All-saving JESUS; therefore let the Christian Triumph in Joy, and hope in Faith; but let the Enemies of Christ, and their owne salvation, be cloathed with shame,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Psal.</hi> 35.2.6. <hi>Psal.</hi> 38. <hi>Esai.</hi> 66.24.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, and cut off from their wicked workes, and become a vile Carkesse, and Reproach, amongst the dead for ever: being destroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Power of Christ's Spirit; that they may not be able to stand against the Glory of God, and their owne Salvation, so that being taken off from their wickednesses, they may be Converted, and arise from the Antichristian Death; by a Spirituall, supernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Resurrection, and Everlasting Life; In Faith through JESUS CHRIST. This we desire; for the worst of Antichristian Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, those Devills in-carnate; the Sectarian Antichrist Apostate Arians; who deny the whole CHRIST, and God, by denying the Covenant of <hi>Generall Redemption.</hi> Let them be confounded, and Perish for ever in their wickednesse; Make them like a Wheele O LORD, and as stubble before the winde of thy Holy Spirit; fill their Faces with shame, that they may seek thy Name, O Lord, for their Salvation, and may know that thou alone, whose Name is <hi>JEHOVAH,</hi> art the Perfect Sanctity, and strength unto all the Earth, and that with thy Church, they may live, and Praise thy Name.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:159779:4"/>
            <head>YEE PEOPLE OF GOD:</head>
            <p>REjoyce in the Glorious Gospel of Christ, and know that now the time is come; that he will bring in his Publique <hi>Monarchiall,</hi> Kingdome, for the Restitution of all things, as hee hath Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised; Of whom the Prophets and Apostles witnesseth: they, both the Patriarkes, Prophets and Apostles, longed for this Kingdome, and all the strength of their Ministrations, and riches of their grace in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Kingdome, was of this Publike Kingdome apart, untill this was revealed, and brought fortth, the Patriarches, Prophets and Apostles still testifying and maintaining Christ the Generall Redeemer, crying out against the world of Opposers, as wicked Adulterers, Abominable Sodomites, spirituall Fornitaoutours, worthy to be condemned for their Reprobate workes, in denying Gods love in Christ, in refusing their own Salvation, turning away to Lyes and crooked pathes of Wickednesse, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so opposing a Spirituall CHRIST, disobeying his Gospel of Order, as it calls to Love, Faith, Mercy, Meeknesse, Righteousnesse, and spirituall walking, in the Grace of Faith: therefore denyers of the Covenant of <hi>Generall Redemption,</hi> and all bruit Beasts, and Hpoycrites, have approved themselves Devills in-carnate; their wickednesse must be destroyed, but their Souls; and Persons shall bee Saved. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>It is desired that the Reader would favourably look at a mistake of a word in the title Page of this Book; and for <hi>Appointted</hi> his Servant, <hi>read</hi> Annointed his Servant.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:159779:4"/>
            <head>DIVINE LIGHT, Manifesting THE LOVE OF GOD UNTO THE WHOLE WORLD: With the True CHVRCH. <hi>Emanuell.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Spirit of the LORD, wee send unto all Saints, and with them unto all People, for their Illumination in the true Christian Faith, which is for Comfort unto Salvation, through Christ our All-saving JESUS, desiring that our God will enlarge your souls unto beleeving, by his <hi>JEHOVAH</hi> Power of the Holy Ghost, opening your soules to see and receive the glorious Goodnesse of our JEHOVAH,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Isai.</hi> 12.2, 3, 4.</note> in his Love, and Perfect righteousnesse in <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi> which is for us his Saints, and for <hi>All,</hi> and the whole Creation, now in due time to be manifested; to the Glory of our Heavenly Father,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 1.2, 3. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.18, 19, 21.</note> and onely Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ, to the comfort of every Creature; and deliverance of the whole Creation, through the Power and Love of our God, <hi>Jehovah,</hi> who in Christ hath, reconciled the World unto himself; by suffering in CHRIST, and meriting
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:159779:5"/>for the Transgressions of his Creation, Angels, and Mankind, and all Immortall Spirits. God so loving the World, as not being willing it should perish for ever,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.14 16, 17. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.9.</note> therefore hee set himself in Christ, to Redeem Us, and to create us anew unto lively Hopes of his love; and everlasting Salvation. Therefore our God, by his JEHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>AH, Power of Love and strength,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5.14, 15.17, 18, 19. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3 5.19, 20, 21, 25.</note> wrought in Christ, his Passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate worke of his owne holy sufferings, to merit our Salvation, and to recover us from our damned condition, wherein we had inthral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led our selves, by departing from the Living God, and obeying the Sophisticall serpent, Called the Devill and Satan, in seeking in our selves for Righteousnesse, wisedome and strengh, In that abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable trangression of our First Parents <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> wee their Children transgressing in the same Line of Rebellion, by Eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Tree of knowledge of <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Evill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.4, 5, 6.1. <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.9. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.3, 6, 7.17, 16. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.10 11.13. <hi>Isai.</hi> 66.17. <hi>Isa.</hi> 12 1, 2, 3, 4, <hi>chap.</hi> 26.4.12. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.9. 13, 14. <hi>Hob.</hi> 2.10, 14, 15. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8.17.10.9.18. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19.21.</note> that is, seeking in our selves for Righteousnesse, thinking to bee wise, and making Our selves like unto God, wee became naked, foolish, blinde and desperately wicked; but our God, comes unto us in <hi>Christ,</hi> pittieth us in the Coole of his Love; the Heate of his wrath, and Anger, being Pacified by his owne Passionate sufferings; In that Heavenly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict which the Deity &amp; Trinity of Persons had in Christs humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, when our God lovingly set himself to worke our Salvation, to Redeem us, and all from Sinne, Curse, Bondage, and Torment. Infinite is the love of our Jehovah, and his Power of Love unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistable, who made his love to overcome his <hi>Justice</hi> so, as yet to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie his <hi>Justice</hi> meritoriously superabundant, paying the Price of our Transgression, and the Transgression of all, Angels, Spirits, and Mankind, sealing the Pardon of all with the Blood of Christ, the Holy <hi>Covenant,</hi> of <hi>Generall Redemption,</hi> our God so Loving the world, as to Perfect his Love unto Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festation, by the Offering up CHRIST, his Sonne,<note place="margin">After the Seal of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Resurrection, shall be no Inquisition for sing <hi>Elijah</hi> comes before that dreadfull day unto Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Elijah</hi>'s Ministry is to Proclaime the good Tydings, and to remove the Curse, and tread down Antichrist.</note> once for <hi>All,</hi> a Token of his Love, making Christ so Perfect a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice <hi>Propitiatory,</hi> that is, Perfect for satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and Mediation, and Advocation, in Propitiation unto the End of <hi>Esau<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:159779:5"/>World, and comming in of <hi>Jacobs,</hi> against the Evill and Filth of sinnes uncleanness, not onely working the Redemption of Us the Elect; but which is wonderfull, making Christ perfect, A Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, as that hee should seale Testimoniall the Love or God not only to us the Elect;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.5.10, 12, 13, 16, 17. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.1, 2. 1 <hi>I<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h.</hi> 3.1, 2.</note> but as Perfect for the Sinnes of the whole world: It is t ue, that he hath magnified his Love wonderfully unto his E<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ect: as the holy Spirit by <hi>Iohn</hi> noteth, saying, <hi>B<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hold what manner of Love the Father hath Loved us. That we should bee called the sonnes of God,</hi> as the Spirit by <hi>Ezekiell</hi> noteth, <hi>That wee should be made such a blessed seed, somes and Daughters unto God,</hi> to hold forth and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st the Glory of his Love, to the Praise of his <hi>Free-Grace,</hi> shining forth to Enlighten, and Enliven the Dead, Darke and blind world;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.22, 23. <hi>Isai.</hi> 61.9. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Ro.</hi> 9.29.</note> this is wonderfull in the workings of our God, which made the Prophets and Apostles to admire, and to long for the comming of this <hi>Zion,</hi> this <hi>Mount Zion,</hi> these sonnes and Daughters of God, who should manifest the Glory of Gods love in Christ unto their fellow Creatures, even the whole Creation, specially the Poore and needy in Reprobate Condition,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Isai.</hi> 40.9. <hi>Psal.</hi> 53.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.18, 19, 21, 23. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.3, 4, 5, 6.12. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.8.16. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.2. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18, 19.20. Zac. 9.11.</note> who being a long time out of Grace, were grinded with the Curse, and Confusion, unto horrour and torment; wee Confirme, <hi>that Gods Love unto his Elect Sonnes and Daughters, is great in such Particularity, making them so blessed: A Fi<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st-fruits m<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st Glorious of the Workes of Redemption unto him, through CHRIST.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in a generall case, and consideration, how wonderfull is the Love and Power of our JEHOVAH, the Blessed <hi>Trinity,</hi> in the sealing Ministry of <hi>Generall Redemption,</hi> wrought through the Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sionate worke of God in Christ, It is true, as the Spirit saith, Our God is LOVE; and this <hi>JEHOVAH,</hi> God Love, smote the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of Darknesse, and triumphed over Justice and Wrath, so glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously, that he obtained in Christ Salvation for <hi>All,</hi> not onely for us the <hi>Elect,</hi> but for the whole World; therefore this is most won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull, as <hi>John</hi> saith in such Case. That Jesus Christ, the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, is not onely a Sacrifice Propitiatory, that is, Testimoniall, and Mediating, advocatory for the sinnes of the <hi>Elect,</hi> but as perfect, for the sinnes of the whole World, to the destroying of Death and Hell, to the delivering of the whole Creation, to the Consumation of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and all Lyars, and all their Lying Vanities, because
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:159779:6"/>our God will now manifest, that he gave Christ to lay downe his life <hi>A Ransome for All,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16</note>
               <hi>God so loved the World,</hi> and Christ came delighting to do the Will of his Father in this, and therefore Christ laid downe his life <hi>A Ransome for All,</hi> as he witnesseth, saying, <hi>No man taketh my life from me; but I lay downe my life of my self; I</hi> (saith Christ,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>chap.</hi> 10.15, 17, 18.</note>) <hi>have Power to lay it downe, and have Power to take it againe, therefore doth my Father love me, because I lay down my life for the sheep.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true, when Christ nameth the sheep, hee speaketh chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fly of his Elect, because the <hi>Elect</hi> were to be made from all Eternity in <hi>Esaus</hi> world of the Curse,<note place="margin">The Elect and Reprobate in their severall cases in <hi>Esaus</hi> world, which is the world of Curse, have suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with God; and Christ onely suffered meritoriously. For all the Saints suffer to witnesse God and Christ's sufferings; the Wicked suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for a time, because they obey not the Gospel, but all sufferings came on all, by the meanes of sinne and the Curse.</note> of the suffering Body of Christ; for although God Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed us and all in Christ, from the totall and Everlasting stroake of Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, yet sinnes Transgression was so great, that untill the comming of <hi>Jacobs</hi> world, The whole Creation in an Externall case of suffering, have tasted of the fruit of the Tree of the knowledge of <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Evill,</hi> so as to suffer with God, but no Creature suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth meritorious for satisfaction, but onely they suffer to taste the Fruit of Rebellion, not so as to be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for ever, but that wee may see what the Evill of him brought in, that wee departed from the perfect Righteousnesse of God, which was acted in that Transgression of our First Parents <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore know, that all Salvation for <hi>All,</hi> now in due time to be manifested, was perfectly wrought of God in his owne Power of Love, strength and good will, through JEHOVAH mercies in Christ; God setting himself in his lost Creatures stead,<note place="margin">Christ in his humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, feared when the Godhead and Trinity of Persons came</note> namely the whole Creation, God the Blessed <hi>Trinity,</hi> the <hi>Three Persons</hi> in unity, in their <hi>Jehovah</hi> Power, in the Spirit of the Deity, setting themselves in Christs <hi>humanity,</hi> the 3. <hi>Persons in mity,</hi> making one God, &amp; Great
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:159779:6"/>
               <hi>downe in him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">JEHOVAH, full of Love, God Love, in fullnesse of all <hi>Charity,</hi> Exercising Love and Mercies unto the worst of Enemies, for wee were all Enemies to God by our Transgression.</note>
               <hi>in their Ʋn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, their spirituall Power of strength, Wisedome and Love to suffer; therefore Christ in his Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture fearing,</hi> Prayed, <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if if it be possible, let this Cup passe from me.</hi> Mat. 26.38, 39, 42.</p>
            <p>Therefore God in his Unction; that is to say, the fulnesse of his Unction not a part of his Unction, for there are three kindes of sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Power working the salvation of all in his Unction: Namely, Saving-Strength, Wisedome, and Love, in the fulnesse of his spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuallity and Power of the Deity in the Trinity of Persons; <hi>Father, Son,</hi> and <hi>holy Ghost,</hi> the whole <hi>God-head</hi> set it selfe bodily in Christ, to suffer for their <hi>Transgressing Creature,</hi> to perfect us by Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and new Creating us, because wee had spoiled our selves in our <hi>First Creation</hi> in Blessed Condition.</p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>Jehovah,</hi> strength of the whole <hi>Trinity</hi> were forced to assume the whole Power of the <hi>Godhead,</hi> in the fulnesse of their Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence and Unction in Holy Workings, to suffer that Passionate suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings which was due to our sinnes transgressions, and the Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressions of the whole Creation; This was the Passionate worke and sufferings of the Godhead, placed in Christs Humanity, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Redemption for <hi>All,</hi> which caused that <hi>Bloody sweat</hi> from the browes of our suffering Saviour,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 22.42.44.</note> when the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head entered the Passionate worke in him in the Garden;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.9, 10, 14. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.10. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17, 18, 19, 21. <hi>Ephes.</hi> 3, 9, 10, 12.</note> Thus <hi>God was in Christ, reconciling the World to himself, by not imputing our sinnes unto us,</hi> for then we had been totally damned, but God love, in his JEHOVAH strength, takes our distressed and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Cause in Consideration, and not willing that we should perish for ever, and seeing that his Justice must be satisfyed, and our Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some paid, and we were not able to satisfie his <hi>justice,</hi> his infinite <hi>ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice,</hi> because we were but lost <hi>creatures,</hi> accursed and damned Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressours, wholly lost in our selves, having no strength, or worth to pay the price of our <hi>Redemption,</hi> nor to suffer for the least sinne.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:159779:7"/>
            <p> Therefore our God was forced to set himself in the lost Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures stead, to act those Sufferings which were due to sinnes trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressions, which his Justice did require, and would not be dispen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with, not satisfyed, except there were a Suffering Satisfactory for the Transgressours; therefore God set himself in Christ's Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, in his Unction and Essence of his <hi>Deity,</hi> to worke out our Salvation,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17.18, 19 21.14. <hi>chap.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.8 <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.4, 5, 13, 14 16. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Isa.</hi> 53.3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.12 <hi>ch.</hi> 10.5.10, 12, 14. <hi>Iohn</hi> 12.32. <hi>ch.</hi> 3.14. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3 21. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Isai.</hi> 26.4. <hi>ch.</hi> 12.2, 3. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.5.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.18, 19, 22 <hi>Zach.</hi> 9.12.</note> setting his Love against his Justice, and suff<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ring in Christ, for the Transgression of Angels, Spirits, and Mankind, hee made his JEHOVAH, Power of Love, to triumph in his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies against his Justice; Therefore the Passion of God in Christ, is the seale of <hi>Salvation</hi> and <hi>Redemption</hi> unto <hi>All,</hi> most perfect. God in Christ Reconciling the World unto himself; for in the Passionate Worke of the Godhead in Christ, Christ's Humanity was afficted for <hi>all Men,</hi> and Angels, for all Transgressours, Angels, Spirits, and mankind; for God set Christ in the place for all Transgres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sours, making Christ, by the Passionate worke of God in him, a Sanctified All-sufficient Sacrifice, by once being offered by the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Spirit; that is, the efficacy of the God-head, in their Love offering up Christ in his Humanity, to satisfie their Justice, and to be the Testimony of seal; by the powring forth his heart-blood, the life of his Humane Nature, for the washing away the sinnes of the whole World; Thus God was in Christ; Thus Christ Suffered, and offered up himself by the Eternall Spirit, to cut off the Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sations of Satan, in an <hi>accusing Conscience,</hi> and to Convince the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleeving, and blind World, and all Hipocrites, calling them to have hope in <hi>God Love,</hi> who <hi>gave his only begotten Sonne, to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the sinnes of the whole World;</hi> A token that God loved the world, so as to Redeem it, and deliver it in due time, which now draweth nigh.</p>
            <p>Therefore thou that sentest unto us; trust in the LORD JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HOVAH, for in the LORD Jehovah is everlasting strength, That is to say, Everlasting increasing superaboundant overflowing in strength of Love, and Jehovah Mercies unto all, specially his <hi>Elect,</hi> more particularly his Predestinated Sonnes and Daughters, the chief part of his Election, in and by whom, hee hath appointed to reveale himself in the great glory of his Jehovah Mercies unto those in Reprobate Condition, unto whom also hee will reward
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:159779:7"/>double, for all their Torment and Losses in Grace and Glory, wherein they were spoyled in <hi>Esaus</hi> world of the Curse, now al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most passed away, but in the world of <hi>Iacobs</hi> blessednesse, now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring in. The Reprobate condition of men and Angels, shall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gained, cursednesse shall be taken away, death and Hell shall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Isai.</hi> 25.6, 7, 8. <hi>chap.</hi> 26.19. <hi>Hos.</hi> 13.14. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.54, 55.57. <hi>Zac.</hi> 9.11 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18, 19, 20, 21.</note> the Grave shall deliver up her dead, all shall be created a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new to life and Immortallity; The damned Prisoners shall be sent forth out of the Pit, wherein there is no water, by the Power of the holy Ghost, who will maintains, and make use of the Blood of Christ, shewing it to be the holy Covenant of <hi>Generall Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; As for thee also, by the bl<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed of thy Covenant,</hi> saith the holy Ghost, speaking to Christ, I <hi>have sent forth thy Prisoners cut of the Pitt, wherein there is no water.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So glorious will our God be seene for the Restitution of all things. Therefore let your soules<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Let the choice Elect, and Predestinated, with all other the People of the LORD; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce to beleeve, trusting in the LORD, resting with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, hoping for his great mercies, for this is most bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed.</hi> Psal. 130.5, 6, 7, 8. Psal. 147.11. <hi>Isai.</hi> 12.1, 2, 3. <hi>Isai.</hi> 26.3, 4 <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.8, 9, 10, 11. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.3.10.17. <hi>chap.</hi> 2, 4, 5, 7, 8, 16. <hi>chap.</hi> 3.9, 10, 11, 12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2, 3, 4, 5. <hi>chap.</hi> 2.6.</note> rest upon the Arke of God, and his Truth, his holy Covenants of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise in Christ, through Christ; for God will be seen in his Love unto all in Christ, because the Godhead wrought their Passionate worke in Christ, conjoyning Christ's <hi>Humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> with them, to suffer for all Angels, Spirits and Mankind; Therefore God hath given Christ in his Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, glory above all; making Christ the Captaine of Salvation unto all, That all things in heaven, and in earth, and hell, may bow be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, because the Father hath made him Lord over all, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the Holy Ghost, rejoycing to receive all their Glory in him, and by him to themselves, for the whole Godhead will be seene in their Glory in CHRIST, and will gather all things unto themselves, in everlasting blessednesse in CHRIST, as CHRIST is now to appeare a Spirituall CHRIST, and All-saving JESUS: That is, being cloathed with the full power of Jehovah, the Holy Ghost; For although the whole
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:159779:8"/>Trinity be called Jehovah by a Conjunction in unity of the Three Persons, yet the Father and the Sonne, doe admit, and commit all their strength for the Restituting and delivering the whole Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto the ministration of the <hi>holy Ghost,</hi> the <hi>Third</hi> Person in the <hi>Trinity;</hi> And therefore the <hi>holy Ghost</hi> is called JEHOVAH by an Emphasis of speech, and therefore it is, that those that have been damned in <hi>Esaus</hi> world of the Curse, could not be delivered, untill the Holy Ghost come in full Power of <hi>Jehovah</hi> strength, in the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of all Charitable mercies unto every Creature, of Angells, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and Mankind; likewise because all Power is committed to the Holy Ghost, to Exhoist and manifest Christ a Spirituall Christ, and All-saving JESUS: Therefore the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> saith, speaking to Christ, as just Judge, condemning, damning and Tormenting a part of his Creation; As for thee, saith the Holy Ghost, speaking unto Christ,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zac.</hi> 9.11, 12.</note>
               <hi>I have sent forth thy Prisoners out of the Pit, wherein is no wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> Therefore turne unto the strong hould, yee Prisoners of hope, of all sorts, for though you have no hope in your selves, there is hope in God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore look unto him all you ends of the Earth, and be ye saved, for now the Curse hasteneth to depart away,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Esai.</hi> 45.21, 22.</note>
               <hi>and everlasting Righteousnesse shall be established.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The glory of the LORD shall be revealed unto all flesh, and the Time hasteneth, that all Eyes shall see it together,<note place="margin">Wee call them Reprobates but only for Distinction; the better to manifest what <hi>Paul</hi> meant also to confound Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ with his owne weapon; that Antichristians may be brought to see, that the damned shall be saved, for Christ de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scended into Hell, to break their hands, Preaching Peace unto them. <hi>1 Pet. 3.18, 19. Ephes. 4.9, 10. Zac. 9.11.</hi>
               </note> and all the ends of <hi>Esaus</hi> world shall see the Salvation of our God, and it shall be known unto all, that the Terestriall part of the Creation, shall live Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally by the Power Celestiall; The Celestiall is Christ and his Elect, God and his holy Angels; the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>restiall is that part of the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which <hi>Paul</hi> calleth the <hi>Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate part,</hi> yet neither Prophet, nor Apostle, nor Patriarke else, durst ever call them Reprobates; onely wee use <hi>Pauls</hi> Expression, to satisfie those Devills Hypocrites, the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:159779:8"/>Antichristian People, who because <hi>Paul</hi> calls them Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, think they should not be saved, they being ignorant that they themselves are some of them, which their wicked workes doe manifest, seeing that they denie the Lord that bought them; in that they deny Christ to be the the <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Redemer;</hi> Those are the Denyers of God and Christ, who doe not beleeve that all things are perfected of God himselfe in Christ, in the Passionate worke of the Trinity in Christ, and the offering up of Christ, an All-sufficient Sacrifice <hi>for the sinnes of the whole world;</hi> there are many degrees of denyere of God and Christ, but all issue forth in their wickednesse, by two cheif Heads and Gates of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry.</p>
            <p>The first pretend to perfect themselves for God and Christ, by selfe Sanctifications, by works of the Law, which they call <hi>Preparations to come unto God and Christ,</hi> being made fit, as they say; In this Range of Errours, with lying vanities, the <hi>Papists, Turkes</hi> and <hi>Protestants</hi> come in thick, working all their Treasons against God and Christ.</p>
            <p>The<note n="*" place="margin">These are such which Seperate themselves, sensuall, having not the Spirit.
<p>Of trus Faith; These thinke none shall be saved, but such as san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie themselves by a forme of faith: these abuse the case of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Predestina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, teaching that none, shall be saved but onely as they call themselves Beleevers. These know not, that Christ laid downe hie life to Ransom all in due time. <hi>1 Tim. 2.4, 6. 1 Joh. 2.2.</hi> Zack. <hi>9. li. Rom. 8.18.19, 21, 22. Rom. 11.32, 33, 34, 36. Act. 3.21.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <hi>Second</hi> are the Idolaters of Formall Faith, who misconstruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the right and true Faith, raise up their formall Faith to be a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit-monging Faith,<note place="margin">Jude 19.</note> under a Rule of worke from the Law of self-sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, likewise these be the sort of unilluminated People, who thinke, yea Proclaime and Preach, that none can be saved, but by such their merit-monging Faith, which is no true Faith, because it is not Christian, vocall or working Faith, for the least graine of true Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:159779:9"/>Faith, removes the mountaines of sinnes, not onely for our selves, but for others; and this Christian vocall Faith,<note place="margin">The meritmongers are as arch Papists as <hi>Belarmine;</hi> though not in the same cause of working to deny Christ.</note> is the true Faith, but the merit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monging faith of <hi>Schismaticks,</hi> is but a Formall Faith, most <hi>Papisticill,</hi> and enthralleth the Creation, and is the same work of merit-monging with the <hi>Morall Law,</hi> only it hath more shew of Gospel in the eyes of the Ignorant, then the Externall Rule of work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Law hath, because it forms its self a Faith, and talks much of Christ, but it is the very mystery of Iniquity in one sense, for it alwayes leanes upon a work; also in the formall Faith of Scismaticks there is a Positive denyall of the work of <hi>Generall Redemption,</hi> and so it Proclaimes openly against Gods Love and Perfection unto his whole Creation in Christ, and therefore it hath caused so many to goe downe into damnation since the Reigne of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ, which Reigne of Antichrist hath been ever since the First <hi>Adam,</hi> but chiefly exalted in <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi> and since the descease of the Apostles, it hath exalted it selfe unto these times, and now the Mystery of Iniquity is a sealing up by the River of <hi>Sedom,</hi> in the Land of <hi>Egypt</hi> in the <hi>North;</hi> In the Great waters <hi>Ephrates,</hi> whose great streames of selfe Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse hasteneth now to be dryed up by the hot Sunne-shine of the Everlasting Gospel of GODS Love in CHRIST unto every Creature;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jere.</hi> 46.6, 7, 10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.12.</note> A way shall be made for the <hi>Kings</hi> of the <hi>East,</hi> namely, the true Beleevers who doe see them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and the whole Creation to bee most Perfect in God through Christ,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.12. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.23.</note> being sanctified, Justifyed and Redeemed from the Evill of sinne and Curse, because God hath made CHRIST our Wisedome,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30, 31.</note> Righteousnesse, Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Redemption.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:159779:9"/>
            <p> The true Faith, the Christian vocall or working Faith, which the Holy Ghost, Christ, the Patriarkes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16.18.36. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.6.8. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.2.</note> Prophets and Apostles, doe so much commend unto all in Scripture and called for at our hands, in case of Salvation, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it, or damnation in refusing it. This true Christian vocall Faith is, to beleeve the <hi>Covenant</hi> of <hi>Generall Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption,</hi> according to the Doctrine of the Patriarkes, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apostles, and as the Spirit by the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> affirmeth.</p>
            <p>That Christ laid <hi>downe his life a Ransome for All, yea for the sinnes of the whole world, as also in Chief for his Elect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Christian Faith leaneth only upon God in Christ; all the Damned that did not, or doe not receive it, must be saved by this Faith; this Faith is Perfect unto all,<note place="margin">These the Patriarks, Prophets and Apostles, and Saints, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>love and maintaine the Covenant of <hi>Generall Redemption,</hi> are onely the true Church of whom CHRIST is the Head.</note> through God himself in Christ.</p>
            <p>Christ in his Church houlds this Faith for his whole Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in due time to be manifested, with the blessed Fruits thereof un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to life and Salvation for All.</p>
            <p>Christ calls for this Faith at the hands of all, but they would not obey.<note place="margin">Matth. 16.18. <hi>chap.</hi> 21.21.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore a time millions of Thousands were damned by their Antichristian workes: yet not damned to perish for ever; for there is none can be damned Totally, but onely in their owne account they are damned, totally and wholly lost in themselves for a time, but the Power of God in CHRIST,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Note well Matth.</hi> 16.18. <hi>chap,</hi> 17.20.</note> and his Church namely those Sonnes and Daughters of GOD, in whom the Spirit keepeth Vocall Faith, so that the Gates of Hell shall not prevaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst it.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:159779:10"/>
            <p> These shall hold forth the Glory of God in true faith; and all that ever dyed in Infidelity,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.19.21.</note> or what sinne soever, shall returne into the liberty of these Sonnes of <hi>God,</hi> for the whole Creation, in respect of the multitudes of the Creation, have ever in <hi>Esaus</hi> world of the Curse, been shut<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.32. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.22, 23. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10, 11, 12.</note> up from this true Faith; but not that they should perish for ever, but rather that God might shew the Glory of his Love and JEHOVAH Power, as also for a time correcting the blood-thirsty and cruell <hi>Caines</hi> and <hi>Judas,</hi> and the Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever, as also the Naturall Bruits of the <hi>Heathen</hi> whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever; yet including all in unbelief;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.32. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.22.</note> not for their totall dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, but rather to set forth the Glory of his JEHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VAH Love, in having mercy on all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh the Deeps of the riches,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.33.</note>
               <hi>both of the Wisedome and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God in his love and JEHOVAH workings, how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>searchable are his Judgements! and his waies past finding out:</hi> by <hi>Drunkards</hi> of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> and vaine Antichristians,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Isai.</hi> 21.1, 7, 12, 13. <hi>chap.</hi> 55.8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13. <hi>Psal.</hi> 25.12, 14. <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.19, 20, 21.22. <hi>Ephes.</hi> 3.3, 4, 5, 9. <hi>Psalm.</hi> 100.1.5.98.1, 2, 3. <hi>Psal.</hi> 22.27, 30, 31.</note> who doe not seek after the minde of God in his Love, in his wayes and workes of mercy unto his whole Creation; but the Lord will reveale his secrets unto his Saints, and unto his People, which have sought him in his Love, and delighted to wait on him in his wayes of mercies; they shall set forth his Glory, and declare his Righteousnesse unto the Generations that are to come: henceforth, and for ever; and all the Generations that are deceased in the old world of <hi>Esau,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.1, 2, 9, 10, 11.</note> shall arise by glorious Resurrections, after the generall Resurrection,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.25, 26, 27. <hi>chap.</hi> 1.10, 11.12.</note> and shall see <hi>the loving kindnesses of the Lord, in the land of the living,</hi> the <hi>new Heavens, and new Earth; The Church, the Saints, the New Jerusalem, and Holy City, now preparing, by the Spirit to be manifested for the blessing and comfort of the whole Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:159779:10"/>
            <p> The true Christian vocall Faith alwayes maintaineth the Covenant of <hi>Generall Redemption,</hi> and that <hi>Christ laid downe his life a Ransome for all, to take away in due time the sinnes of the whole world, in manifestation,</hi> that all shall see, feele, and possesse the Blessednesse of it to their everlasting salvation and comfort. This Christian vocall Faith wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to receive all things from Gods free Love, and Great Jehovah Mercies: Seeing and beleeving, that although there were but Three Persons Beleevers in the Earth with Christ, yet God will have his whole Creation, although not any else did beleeve but these three, in and with Christ; but there hath been Millions of Thousands in all ages, in the worst of times, that have had the lively Power of these feeds of Faith in them internally, though not manifested to themselves and the world; also there hath been some in all Ages, which had the seeling of this Faith, and openly professed it: There were Three that gave themselves to the Fiery Furnace in <hi>Nebuchadnezers</hi> dayes, for this Faith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.12.16, 17, 18, 23, 25, 27, 28.</note> and in this worst of Ages; now there is a seed, although they be but few in visible appearance, like the gleaning Grapes, when the vintage is done.</p>
            <p>These make a noise, as through wine, in the Profession of this Faith; these cry aloud from the <hi>Sea's,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zac.</hi> 9.15, 16.17. <hi>Isai.</hi> 24.13, 14, 15. <hi>chap.</hi> 61.9. <hi>chap.</hi> 65.8, 9.</note> listing up their voice, singing and rejoycing in their souls, for the Majestie of the LORD on High.</p>
            <p>These are the Sonnes and Daughters of God; these are the seed of Blessednesse, maintaining the Christian Faith, <hi>That Christ laid downe his life a Ransome for all, and that every Immortall Creature is made Perfect by God himself in Christ;</hi> these are those Beleevers in whom all Nations shall be bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed through Christ; The King of Righteousnesses, and King of such his Saints, for their glory and defence.</p>
            <p>These Beleevers are that seed of Blessednesse unto all the Creation, with them, in them, and by them; the whole Creation shall receive Blessednesses through the mighty Power of God in Christ, which as the Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles witnes in the behalf of all the Rebellious unbeleevers,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:159779:11"/>saying, <hi>Except the Lord of Hosts, and God of Sabbath had left us a seed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jsai.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.29.</note> speaking in the behalfe of the world, wee had been as <hi>Sodoms,</hi> and should have been made like unto <hi>Gome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rab.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh Infinite is the blessednesse of such a People, such Sonnes and Daughters of God, who are made Instrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall meanes of God through Christ, only by beleeving, and declaring his Goodnesse, and in their Spirits, contesting with God for his JEHOVAH mercies towards the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious, in such their spirituall worship, they are made Instruments of Blessing unto the whole Creation, although there should be but Three in the whole Earth; but there are many in the earth, and they are the Power of the Kingdom of God, Ch ist's Publique Monarchiall Kingdom now appearing.<note place="margin">Christ in his private King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome s<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e judge over the quick and dead, to condemne, and execute Torments on the Rebellious, whom he held as Prisoners for a time, <hi>Zac. 9.11.</hi> But Christ in his publike Kingdome, by the Power of the Holy Ghost, shall reigne for ever, to bring up all to life and Immortallity: the Holy Ghost, for the Father, and Christ shall execute the judgement of Love &amp; Mercies unto all, to the destroying of Death, and Hell, and delivering of all forts of Prisoners. <hi>Zac. 9.11. Hos. 13, 14. Isai. 25.8. 1 Cor. 15.55.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore let all the sc<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>les and Spirits of the People of our God rest on our JEHOVAH. For now the waters of troubles are abated, and in the New Heavens, and New earth of Christs Publike Kingdome: there shall be no more Sea of Antichristian Mysteries, nor of the Spirits contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the Creation: for God will manifest Himselfe in his love unto every Creature; onely the old Heavens and earth of <hi>Antichrists</hi> wickednesses, must be burnt up with the fire of Gods Spirit; yea, all things naturall, and super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall
<pb facs="tcp:159779:11"/>must be changed at these Resurrections now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</p>
            <p>The Private Kingdome of Christs Justice must passe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to give place to the publike Kingdome of God the Father, in his Jehovah Mercies unto all; And the Father will glorifie Christ, to give him the ruling of it for ever; who shall commit it to the holy Ghost, to enliven all things, to regulate and comfort, enlarging all things in blessed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, renewing all things, and stablishing all things for ever unmooveable; so that the Heavens and the Earth in their fourefold considerations, shall be changed from Corruption to incorruption; from sinne and curse, to blessednesse; from effeminacy and bondage, to strength and Freedome in blessednesses; and the Heavens and the Earth shall not be destroyed, as drowly drunken <hi>Ephraemites,</hi> and blinde <hi>Egyptians</hi> doe imagine, out of their owne evill hearts, by misconstructing the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Marke, when the holy Ghost speaketh of entring Christs Publike Kingdome, which wee call the Kingdome of the Father, given unto Christ; and the holy Ghost, for to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt the Glory of the Father in.</p>
            <p>The holy Ghost speaking unto Christ, as Judge in his private Kingdome.</p>
            <p>The Spirit rejoyceth, saying; As for thee, by the blood of thy Covenant; I, that is to say, the Holy Ghost, have sent forth <hi>thy Prisoners out of the Pits, wherein is no water.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore although it was formerly said, the Arke of the Covenant, of saving but a part of the Creation, must be sought unto;</p>
            <p>Yet now the Lord willeth not that wee should seek unto those <hi>minors</hi> and lesser things of Christs Private Kingdom, but that wee should seek unto him for his Jehovah Power, and glory of his publike Kingdome, in his mercies unto <hi>All;</hi> for his mercies are spread over all his Workes, and hee willeth that wee should speake of the Glory of this Kingdome, and calke of such his Power, declaring such his Noble Acts, in that hee hath Triumphed ever Death, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:159779:12"/>hath led <hi>captivity captive</hi> for <hi>All,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Psal.</hi> 145.1, 2, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13. <hi>Act.</hi> 3.21. <hi>Jere.</hi> 3.16.17. <hi>Isai.</hi> 40.3. <hi>chap.</hi> 52.10. <hi>Isai.</hi> 40.9. <hi>cha.</hi> 42.7.10, 11.16. <hi>chap.</hi> 52.7. <hi>chap.</hi> 61.9, 10, 11. <hi>chap.</hi> 63.7.</note> to the Restituting of all things in due time.</p>
            <p>Therefore our God will not that wee shall say any more, <hi>the Arke of Particular Redemption,</hi> for that must passe away, and shall not come into our mindes, because now the People of God, the <hi>new Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem shall be called the Throne of the LORD; and all Nations shall be gathered to it; and the Glory of the LORD</hi> shall appeare in his loving Kindnesses unto <hi>all Flesh,</hi> and all eyes shall see it together, for the Lord will shew Christ a Spirituall Christ, and All-saving Jesus; But this his Glory shall be seene on the House of <hi>Israel,</hi> and shall shine forth from the House of <hi>Israel</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> spirituall;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joel.</hi> 2.28, 29.32. <hi>chap.</hi> 3.17, 18.</note> his <hi>Mount Sion,</hi> namely the Sonnes and Daughters of God now appearing,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos.</hi> 9.11.13. <hi>Obad.</hi> 21.</note> who shall be strengthened by the Power of the Holy Ghost, and an <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah</hi> Ministry, to declare the loving Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses of the Lord unto All;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Isai.</hi> 25.6. <hi>Isai.</hi> 55.1, 2.</note> that <hi>good ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings;</hi> those comfortable <hi>new Vines,</hi> and <hi>Water of Life</hi> which commeth from this <hi>New Jerusalem,</hi> for from those the Saints, the Sonnes and Daughters of God, which the holy Ghost calleth <hi>Sion,</hi> and <hi>New Jerusalem,</hi> shall flow those streames of <hi>Living water,</hi> by their Doctrine and Profession of God and Christ, which the Spirit calleth <hi>new wine, milke, Honey, and a feast of fat things, of wine upon the lees, well refined;</hi> thus in a spirituall sense, the Holy Ghost laboureth to set out the glory of God in his love <hi>unto All,</hi> by the comming of the Sonnes and Daughters of GOD, and Glorious <hi>Mount Sion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.22, 23. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22, 23, 24. <hi>Isai.</hi> 51.16. <hi>ch.</hi> 52.1, 2. <hi>chap.</hi> 40.9. <hi>Psal.</hi> 87.2.3. <hi>Psal.</hi> 5.2.</note> the Church of the Living God, unto whom the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:159779:12"/>Assembly of Saints, and all * Nations and Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons must be gathered, as the Patriarks, Prophets,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Isai.</hi> 2.2, 3, 4. <hi>Psal.</hi> 138.4.5. <hi>Psal.</hi> 22.27.</note> and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, by the Holy Spirit have testified, they<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Psal.</hi> 53.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.23. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.39, 40. <hi>Psal.</hi> 102.13.15, 16, 2. <hi>Esdras.</hi> 13.35, 36. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</note> themselves longing, groaning and waiting with the whole Creation, for the comming of these most mighty Sonnes and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of God, these true Beleevers, for they without us could not be made perfect, untill this <hi>Sion</hi> appeare in it's Glory, which now hasteneth to * come; it must be noted, that the Arke of the Covenant is taken in Scripture in a two-sold consideration in one speciall Case; First, as it hath Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unto the Covenant of the <hi>Morall Law,</hi> for self-sanct fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, by worke of Formall Faith, manifesting unto the world but a particular Election, or a part thereof to be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; Yet in this manifesting Christ, and so it hath the Title <hi>Acke</hi> from Christ, and thus it stood in the Private Kingdom of Christ, yet so as to shaddow, Typifying in and under a darke Figure, manifesting Christ the Generall Redeemer, yet so as by Legall Covenant with it's serimoniall shadow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing worship, including and keeping all under bondage; because it would teach Christ no farther a Generall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, then black <hi>Mount Sinai</hi> mysteries would admit, and therefore in this sense, the Spirits reprehends it, and calls all people to come off from it in those dayes, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Ye shall not seek unto the Arke of such selfe-sanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Covenant,</hi> neither shall they remember it, saith the Lord;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 3.16.</note> neither shall it come to minde; neither shall they visite it, saith the Lord; neither shall that be done any more, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it is contrary to the <hi>Covenant</hi> of <hi>Generall Redemption,</hi> and contrary to the perfecting the whole Creation. No, it never perfected any one,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jere.</hi> 31, 32. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.9.</note> although God took them by the hand, strengthened them as a Father, or nourishing them as a Husband; yet none could stand therein, but break it, and in the Issue of all their services, the whole Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is forced to turne from <hi>Mount Sinai,</hi> unto <hi>Mount Sion;</hi> for <hi>Mount Sinai,</hi> Covenant of selfe-sanctification, enthral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.24, 25.</note> and damned the best of it's Disciples; Therefore it is the Covenant of <hi>Generall Redemption,</hi> which is called, The <hi>New
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:159779:13"/>Covenant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joy, Liberty, San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification &amp; strength comes from this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, unto Glory and Triumph. <hi>Jere. 31.31, 33, 34.</hi> Heb. <hi>8.8.10, 11, 12, 13.</hi>
               </note> and this <hi>Covenant,</hi> this <hi>Mount Sion</hi> of the <hi>New Testament</hi> of Christ's Blood, saveth all, and makes all perfect, by taking away the sinnes of all; and this <hi>Covenant</hi> of <hi>Free-Grace,</hi> and <hi>Generall Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption,</hi> delivereth the damned Prison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, which the <hi>First Covenant</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thralled. Secondly, the <hi>Arke,</hi> as exclusive from the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi> of selfe-sanctification, was a figure of Christ in the best sense, pointing out by a figure the <hi>Publike Gospel King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> that now is to appeare; and so the <hi>Arke</hi> was a Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and supporter of the <hi>Covenant</hi> of <hi>Generall Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in Christs Private Kingdome,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deu.</hi> 32.43. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15, 11, 12. <hi>Psal.</hi> 117.1, 2.</note> calling upon all to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Glory of God in Christ, and so as the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies were used in the best sense to shadow out Christ as a Type and Figure of his <hi>Publike Kingdome</hi> now to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare.</p>
            <p>Thus the <hi>Arke</hi> was joyned with the <hi>Law Divine,</hi> and held the <hi>Covenant</hi> of the <hi>Law Divine,</hi> which did witnesse the <hi>Covenant</hi> of <hi>God's Free-grace,</hi> in the <hi>Covenant</hi> of <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Redemption;</hi> and thus being a <hi>Testimony</hi> of <hi>God's Love in Christ,</hi> unto the <hi>whole Creation.</hi> The <hi>Arke</hi> in such sense is commended by the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> and accounted <hi>the Glory of</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.3, 4, 5, 6.21. <hi>chap.</hi> 5.2, 3, 4, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.19.11, 12. <hi>ch.</hi> 6.1, 2, 3, 6, 13.19, 20, 21. 1 <hi>Chro</hi> 14.3.7, 8, 14. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.2, 4 5.12, 13, 14, 15 21, 22.</note>
               <hi>Israel;</hi> and in such spirituall sense, and Gospel Considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by a speech Figurative, the Holy Ghost commendeth the <hi>Arke</hi> of <hi>the Covenant,</hi> now as a Testament of his Love, and in such sense, as a <hi>Spirituall Arke:</hi> Now CHRIST in his Church supporteth the Covenant of <hi>Generall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption,</hi> and the Saints Professing and maintaining against the <hi>Covenant</hi> of selfe-righteousnesse, and selfe-sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the Spirituall Power of Christ in his Church, sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting, Professing and manifesting the <hi>Covenant</hi> of <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Redemption,</hi> and <hi>Gods Free-Grace</hi> and Love unto <hi>All</hi> in CHRIST, this <hi>Arke</hi> of GOD, the Church, the Sonnes and Daughters of God, by the Professing of the true Faith.</p>
            <p>Thus Glory must be given to the GOD of FAITH,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:159779:13"/>THE FATHER OF OUR LORD JESUS CHRIST, WHO IN CHRIST HATH SEALED THE ATONEMENT FOR ALL, TAKING AWAY THE SINNES OF THE WHOLE WORLD. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 22. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4, 6.</p>
            <p>Therefore Blessed are those that seek the Lord in Truth, in his Gospel, of his Love and Mercies unto his whole Creation, The which his Love he hath Sealed unto <hi>All,</hi> with the <hi>Blood</hi> of CHRIST, thereby <hi>taking away the sinnes of the whole World;</hi> Thou that desirest to know the minde of the LORD, his minde is this, That <hi>all men should be saved;</hi> That is, that all should know, both mankind,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4.</note> Angels and Spirits, That God in Christ hath made us his Elect, and with us, all perfect to himself in CHRIST; GOD in CHRIST Reconciling the world unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, by Reconciling himselfe unto the World,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14, 15, 17, 18, 19, 21.</note> God in CHRIST, suffering for his lost Creature, yea his whole Creation, Paying the Price of our Ransome, with the blood of Christ, God in Christ having wrought the Passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate worke of all sufferings due unto our sinnes, and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying his owne Justice by himself, in his passionate suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, in Christs <hi>Humanity,</hi> scourging Christ for all;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Isai.</hi> 53.4.6, 7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. <hi>chap.</hi> 2.9, 14. <hi>cha.</hi> 10.5, 9, 10.13, 14. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6.</note> hee sanctified the Humane Person of Christ to be a Sacrifice sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory <hi>for the sinnes of the whole world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And so Christ is said in one sense, <hi>to lay downe his Life a ransome for All:</hi> but Heathen, and Hypocrites, Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christians and Devills, would<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jude</hi> 5.6.</note> not beleeve, nor receive this Truth in Obedience to the Gospel, and therefore for a time they have damned themselves, being by Christ justly condemned for their unbeliefe and Disobedience, in not obeying the Gospel of Peace, Righteousnesse and Love, to God, and our fellow Creatures.</p>
            <p>Therefore for a time, many Thousands have been im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisoned in the <hi>Pit wherein there is no water;</hi> But JEHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VAH, the Power of Love,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zac.</hi> 9.11,</note> in fulnesse of Charity in the Blessed Trinity, in the Unity of their Unction and Essence in the Spirit of the Deity, in the working Power of Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:159779:14"/>Faith, God, Love, and Great JEHOVAH, who is rich in mercy unto all,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Job.</hi> 4.8.16. <hi>Psal.</hi> 145.9.21.</note> and hath spread his mercy over all his workes, nee, in the Ministry of the Holy Ghost, in due time now comming by the blood of Christ, which he hath made the Covenant of <hi>Generall Redemption;</hi> The <hi>Everlasting Coven<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt;</hi> by this our God will <hi>deliver the Prisoners out of the Pit wherein is no water,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Z<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c.</hi> 9.11, 12</note> which out of Question is the Pit of Hell, which <hi>Dives</hi> complained of, when he cryed to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> for <hi>a drop of water, to coole his Blaspheming tongue,</hi> which had denyed Christ to be the <hi>Generall Redeemer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 16.19, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25.</note> and had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed to shew mercy to the hungry <hi>Lazarus,</hi> the poore Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, lame and diseased souls, of whom <hi>Lazarus</hi> was a Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure; therefore the Lord sets it out by that Parable in the Gospel, to Reprehend the Hypocrites, and Antichristians, the spirituall prowd diseases, and drowsie Drunken Sheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards, who denie the chiefe <hi>Corner-Stone,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Isai.</hi> 28.1, 7, 12, 13, 14, 16, 20.</note> the Doctrine of <hi>Generall Redemption,</hi> and having framed an <hi>Antichristian</hi> forme of Religion, misconstering the case Elective, and wresting the Doctrine of Predestination; they shut out the soules of the ignorant from hope of mercy; and therefore God for a time hath punished many thousands of such Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, that did no<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> beleeve his holy <hi>Covenant</hi> of <hi>Generall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption;</hi> such <hi>Diveses,</hi> and earthy rich in their Pharisismes in Hypocrisies, God hath afflicted after Death, because in this life they walked Prowdly, not obeying his Gospel, and faith of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Patriarkes, Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, who made a Covenant with their Families, that their Children should maintaine and hold forth the Covenant of <hi>Generall Redemption,</hi> which is called the Covenant of our Fathers. <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.10. and the Children like <hi>Pharisees</hi> Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.10, 11, 17, 18, 19. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4, 6. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.2.</note> the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> by <hi>Malachy</hi> reproveth them for it, and bids the Hypocrites and Transgressours Remember, that though they were so wilfully blinde, as not to look and behold Christ to be the <hi>Generall Redeemer</hi> of all. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17, 18, 20, 21. <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.12, 13. <hi>chap.</hi> 2.4, 5, 6, 8, 9, 12, 13. <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Babylon is fallen,</hi> Rev. 18.1, 2, 3, 4. <hi>Esay.</hi> 8.19. <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.21, 26, 27, 28, 30, 31, 32.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:159779:14"/>
            <p> Yet <hi>Malachy</hi> noteth, they could not be so ignorant, but they must know the mystery of <hi>Gods Love</hi> in Christ in the Creation; for saith <hi>Malachy,</hi> we have all one Father, one God hath created us all, and so he reprehends the Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites and Devills, the <hi>Judases</hi> of our times, who with false Prophesying, Peepings and Mutterings, denie Christ to be the <hi>Generall Redeemer</hi> of his whole Creation: And so they denie the Doctrine of Restitution of all things,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 3.21.</note> which God hath promised, and which is sealed, because CHRIST <hi>laid downe his life a Ransome for all;</hi> Therefore <hi>Antichrist,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and all his Disciples are Lyars. A habitation of Devills; a Cage of uncleane and hatefull Birds; a hould of fowle Lying Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, manifested, in that they denie the Covenant of <hi>Generall Redemption;</hi> God is truth, his Word is Truth: which main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth, <hi>That Christ laid downe his life a Ransome for all;</hi> and least the Lyars and Flatters should seduce his People,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2, 4, 6.</note> and passe away unknowne in their Mystery of Iniquity. God and his Word maintaineth, That Christ laid downe his life not onely for us his <hi>Elect,</hi> but as certaine, <hi>for the sinnes of the whole world,</hi> though not in the same case, nor indeed not fully to be manifested untill these times.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.2.</note> And now in due time it is to be manifested to the Tryumph of the People of God: to the bringing in Salvation unto all,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6.</note> with Power in our Christ,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.10.</note> to the Exaltation of his Spirituall Monarchiall Kingdome of Life over <hi>All,</hi> to the <hi>destroying of Death and hell for all, by destroying the Power of the Grave,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Isai.</hi> 25.8. <hi>Hos.</hi> 13, 14. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.8. <hi>chap.</hi> 18.2. <hi>chap.</hi> 11.8. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.15. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.4. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.23. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6. 1 <hi>Job.</hi> 2.2, 1. <hi>Heb.</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.32.</note>
               <hi>to the overthrow and fall of great</hi> Babylon, <hi>and destroying of all Devills therein; to the destroying of</hi> Egypt <hi>and</hi> Sodome, <hi>and raising up the glory of</hi> Israel, <hi>to the turning of</hi> Black-coates white, <hi>destroying the Power of the Dogges of</hi> Antichrist, <hi>the casting downe of fa se Ministry, and raising up the</hi> 24. Elders, <hi>to the comfort of the whole Creation, and Restitution of all things, and bringing in Gospel Perfection to every Creature through Christ, Who laid downe his life a Ransom for</hi> ALL, which the blessed Apo<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tles, <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> will maintaine to the face of the proudest Priest, or new <hi>Lord Popes</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> The Spirit of God calleth to draw neer with a true heart, in fulnesse of Faith:
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:159779:15"/>and so to draw neere, as to drinke of the Fountaine of Gods Love, and as Sonnes and Daughters of God, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve for the unbeleever,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Esai.</hi> 12.2, 3. <hi>Rev.</hi> 23.17. <hi>Isai.</hi> 55.1.</note> and to rejoyce in our Beleeving, seeking in truth of Heart, and in the fulnesse of Charity, the good of all, not fearing the Reproach of the wicked and Unbeleever: And seeking the way of the Gospel: Is to set out Gods Love in CHRIST unto <hi>All,</hi> and every Creature in the fulnesse of Love and Charity,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 1.23.</note> in Purity and Righteousnesse, of Godlinesse in the way of Faith, and that truth, which in Christ's Publick Kingdome sanctifieth the whole Creation, through the Blood of the <hi>Holy Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> of <hi>Generall Redemption.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Isai.</hi> 51.7, 8. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.13, 14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore the Christian must not be ashamed, nor mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the Gospel, but must rejoyce, seeing their way is Righteousnesse and Truth, in Love unto all: Holding forth the great and wonderfull Glory <hi>of God in Christ,</hi> which was appointed to be Revealed in and through<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.18. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.9, 10. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.23.25. <hi>Acts.</hi> 3.19, 20, 21, 22.</note> us, in these times, which are the times for the beginning of <hi>Restitution</hi> in some Degree.</p>
            <p>It is the minde and will of the Lord, that wee should wait on him, so as to walke with him in his Truth, with a good Courage, standing fast unto the Faith, and Trusting in our JEHOVAH, so as to looke for his Great and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expressible Mercies, and Tokens of his Love, unto our selves his Saints in speciall, as also, and as perfect unto eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Immortall Creature with us.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ps<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l.</hi> 147.11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord rejoyceth in a mercy-expecting People, but especially in those that trust in him, and hold fast upon his Love, and wrestle with him in Spirit, for his JEHOVAH strength, and Loving Kindnesses unto all; for in such sense and <hi>Gospel Rule,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark.</hi> 12.30, 31, 32, 33, 34.</note> wee must <hi>Love our Neighbour as our selfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is, desiring, and seeking their Salvation as Perfect as <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur owne, so farre as it is in our strength to doe them good.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:159779:15"/>
            <p> Oh wicked <hi>Antichrist</hi> thou art, whosoever that teache<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> against this Doctrine of <hi>Love unto all.</hi> And this,<note place="margin">Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the world, not to damne for ever. Joh. <hi>3.16.17.19.</hi>
               </note> Oh <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ</hi> thou doest, when thou denyest the <hi>Covenant</hi> of <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Redemption,</hi> which God hath sealed with the Blood of Christ in Love and perfect Charity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God so loving the world, that hee gave his onely begotten Sonne, that whosoever beleeveth in him, should not Perish, but have everlasting life,</hi> for <hi>God sent his Sonne into the World, not to condemne the world, but that the World through him should be saved,</hi> and therefore <hi>Christ laid downe his Life a Ransome for All, for the sinnes of the whole world, and every immortall Creature therein contained.</hi> It is true, God tied it in the first world of <hi>Esau,</hi> unto Faith, as also in this se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond world of <hi>Jacob,</hi> but it is vocall Faith, <hi>Abrahams</hi> Faith, <hi>Esaus</hi> world was not able to beare it, but onely in some, the State Predestinated; but now the Lord will make that Vocall Faith of <hi>Abraham,</hi> to flourish in <hi>Jacobs</hi> world, for he will perfect his Promises, <hi>to restitute all things.</hi> This <hi>Christian Faith</hi> is of Power to bring all things to life: If there were but three Persons in the whole world, that had it in Possession, it receiveth all things from God in Christ, and works through God himself; it is perfect unto all in Christ from God; in due time the Lord will bring it unto its full Birth, to the breaking up the Gates of Hell,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16.</note> and meeting Christ in the <hi>generall Resurrection,</hi> shall receive life and Power to immortallize all things. In the mean while, the Power of this Faith, in its proper workings, is in the Sonnes and Daughters of God, to make them the Church of the Living God, in one degree, and blessed seed, for the good of the whole Creation.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephes.</hi> 1.21, 22, 23. <hi>chap.</hi> 3.9, 10, 11, 12.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the Gospel affaires, let the Christian soule rest waiting upon God, not regarding the Distractions in the Earth; for <hi>Antichrist</hi> must be shaken out of the earth; and there are many <hi>Antichrists,</hi> some are willing to set out Christ so farre as they know;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.18. <hi>chap.</hi> 4.3.</note> yet it must alwayes bring some vaine-glory, and this makes them little <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christs.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:159779:16"/>
            <p> Other <hi>Antichrists</hi> are Deadly malicious against Christ, and these are the Arch-Antichristians; these regard not the true God, neither true Doctrine, nor true Church Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, such as may set out the glory of GOD, and his CHRIST, these labour to set up Forms of Religion, and forms of Doctrine, such as may serve to uphold their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichristian Kingdome,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1, 2. <hi>Iude</hi> 4.</note> and harden People in their Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenismes; these labour to denie GOD and CHRIST, and their owne Salvation, under cunning pretences; wrest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the whole Scriptures, falsefying and misconstructing the Case of <hi>Election</hi> and <hi>Predestination,</hi> making as though none should ever be saved but the <hi>Elect</hi> and <hi>Predestinated;</hi>
               <note place="margin">It is in Case di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctinctive betweene the Choice Elect, and Predestinated; the Royall Church, and the World; for the World and the Church are to be considered with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinction. <hi>Ezek. 14.22, 23.</hi>
               </note> It is true, in Case Distinctive, none shall ever be saved with such Glorious Salvation as the <hi>Predestinated,</hi> and <hi>Elect;</hi> For the Royall part of the Three degrees of <hi>Election,</hi> are <hi>The Church of</hi> CHRIST, <hi>The</hi> Sonnes <hi>and</hi> Daughters <hi>of</hi> GOD, <hi>The</hi> Elect, that it is impossible for <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist</hi> to Deceive them.</p>
            <p>The Case of <hi>Predestination</hi> in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, is that Condition, wherein by Gods fore-knowledge, or which is more perfect,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.3, 4, 5, 6, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17, 18, 19, 21.</note> his owne Decree, before the Worlds began: Hee sealed up in great Love and Mercies, a Part of his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to be made Co-heires, joyn theirs with Christ, in all his Glory, in the greatest of his Glory. So as to become visible unto him; A Church, his body mysticall, as hee is a Spirituall CHRIST; wherein, and by his Church, the <hi>Predestinated</hi> having Christ their Head conjoyned with them in full Spirituallity: In his second comming, these <hi>Predestinated</hi> and <hi>Elect,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Isai.</hi> 61.9. <hi>chap.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.29.</note> the Church should be so gathered by the Spirit out of the word, by the Power of Faith, as to become a <hi>Blessed seed</hi> unto the whole Creation, for the salvation of the whole Creation, through the Power of God in Christ.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:159779:16"/>
            <p> This is that Seed which the Prophets and Apostles wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nessed of, and longed for their comming, when ever this seed did appear visible in any age, the age was blessed in them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gene.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.14.</note> but they were not fully to be manifested,<note place="margin">The Saints by maintaining the Covenant of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with Christ, and for Christ, Prevaile. Rom. <hi>8.19.</hi>
               </note> nor come in their full strength untill now, And now they must grow up by the strength of JEHOVAH, by Degrees, as the Spirit is pleased to Elevate and lift up it self in them. Therefore the State of <hi>Predestination</hi> and <hi>Election,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.1, 2. <hi>Ev. John.</hi> 7.38. <hi>De<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 18.15. <hi>Act.</hi> 3.21. <hi>Isay.</hi> 52.5. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.20, 22, 24. <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.9, 10, 11. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.12, 14, 15. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.4. <hi>Esai.</hi> 40.20 <hi>chap.</hi> 45.26.20.</note> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be particular unto some of the Creation: to save them with such a Glorious Salvation, as to make them Instruments of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto the whole Creation.</p>
            <p>Yet this doth not in the Truth of the Doctrine of <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destination</hi> and <hi>Election,</hi> reach such damned Lessons, as the Heathen doe straine it to, when they Preach none shall be saved but the <hi>Elect</hi> and <hi>Predestinated,</hi> they are notable Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars, as the Spirit noteth. The Priests, and their Disciples must study the Gospel better, for they Blaspheme the LORD, in denying his <hi>Covenant</hi> of <hi>Generall Redemption,</hi> and have misconst<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red the Case of <hi>Election</hi> and <hi>Predestina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> And it is not <hi>Calvin,</hi> not all the Papisticall Bookes of <hi>Romanists,</hi> though never so Refined, that can hide their Hypocrisies; The Spirit of CHRIST will sire their stubble, and consume their G<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uld and Silver, Formes, and all their Graven Images, of Formall Religion, shall be burnt up.</p>
            <closer>
               <hi>Blessed be the GOD of</hi>
               <lb/> Salvation,<lb/> HALELUJAH<lb/>
               <hi>To the Blessed Trinity.</hi>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="statement">
            <pb facs="tcp:159779:17"/>
            <p>
               <hi>According to the</hi> English<lb/>
               <hi>Account,</hi> 1646.</p>
            <p>SEALED<lb/> For Record, <hi>from the</hi>
               <lb/> 20. <hi>of</hi> January<lb/> 1645. <hi>or</hi>
               <lb/> 46.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>